Hello , I 'm Christophe Gans ,
the director of the film you 're going to watch , Silent Hill .
This film
is very important to me
inasmuch as it 's related to another passion of mine ,
besides cinema , which is video games .
I 've made two other feature-length films ,
Crying Freeman and Brotherhood of the Wolf ,
which were films about my passion for cinema ,
Asian cinema
and European genre cinema of the 1960s .
And , of course ,
after a while I wanted to tackle something a bit more personal ,
something less referential ,
and maybe to talk about another
of my hobbies ,
namely video games ,
a domain which , for the moment , is largely uncharted ,
as regards its analysis , as regards its history ...
And maybe this let me make , in Silent Hill ,
not a more personal film ,
but at least a more individual one , than my previous two .
Of course ,
adapting a video game isn 't like adapting a book ,
or remaking another film .
It 's more , for me , like a travel diary .
What I mean is , Silent Hill is a game
in which you can lose yourself .
It takes you on a trip in another world ,
another country , which is , of course , virtual ,
but still very real for the player ,
who spends hours and hours wandering around in it .
And ... and so ,
adapting a video game is quite a special exercise .
I didn 't want the film
to simply have the title Silent Hill .
I didn 't want the film to just be ...
I didn 't want it to simply use the video game .
But I didn 't want it to be just a cinematographic transcription .
I wanted it to be a film about my experience as a player ,
a film which , in a way , communicates
what I feel when I 'm playing .
So it was a bit of a gamble because , in a way ,
it ran counter to certain narrative rules of cinema ,
which are well established ,
and which I consider to be very conservative .
I talked about it to two other directors , who are also gamers ,
Nicolas Boukhrief and Roger Avary .
And we quickly agreed to try an adaptation of Silent Hill ,
the three of us ,
even though Nicolas Boukhrief 's name
only appears at the end of the credits .
In fact , Nicolas Boukhrief was there at the start
of the adaptation of the video game , along with me .
Our job , at first , consisted
of working out how to transfer not the game ,
but our sensations when playing it .
Now of course , Silent Hill
is a town .
It 's a place .
And it remains more a place than a story .
For me it 's sort of The Twilight Zone ,
the equivalent of Rod Serling 's famous TV series ,
a place where anything could happen .
If you were to go there ,
you 'd be confronted with your subconscious , your psyche ,
your fears , obviously , but also perhaps with your hopes .
It 's a universe
that 's deeply mystical ,
so the people who come to Silent Hill
can have different types of experiences .
Quite clearly , in the film ,
the place Silent Hill is a world
where several dimensions meet .
One of these , the fog dimension , is , in a way ...
an expiatory dimension .
It 's sort of the dimension of ... purgatory .
There 's also the rust dimension , which is the dimension of punishment .
Hell .
And at one point in the film I thought it 'd be interesting to show
the paradise dimension .
And this scene under the tree is the scene
which gives us , quite clearly ,
the main character 's own personal paradise .
A simple scene , under a tree , in a field ,
with the daughter she loves more than anything .
As you can see ,
the father , played by Sean Bean ,
has quickly been pushed to one side in the narrative .
That was my intention .
I wanted the character played by Sean Bean
to appear at the beginning and the end ,
and for the film proper to have only female characters .
And then the studio which pre-bought the film , TriStar ,
asked for more of the male character .
They were very good to me ,
very flexible and indulgent .
Their only request was for the male character to appear more .
They were worried the film would become too feminine ,
and that some of its basic audience ,
who are obviously teenagers and young men ,
because the whole world of video games
is still very male ...
Less so , but it 's still the case .
So they asked me for a man .
So we carefully slipped in Sean Bean 's character
throughout the film .
This caused problems , which I 'll come back to ,
but it was their only request .
I tried to make sure that the atmosphere and rhythm of the film
took their cue from the music .
The music for the film ,
which was rearranged rather subtly by Jeff Danna ,
is in fact the work of Akira Yamaoka ,
who has been the producer of the series Silent Hill ,
since Silent Hill 2 .
He 's the embodiment , if you like ,
of orthodox Silent Hill-ness , if such a thing exists .
And Akira Yamaoka ... It was very important to me that the film music
should be music written by Akira Yamaoka .
When you play the game ,
you are immersed , often for hours at a time ,
in this music ,
so I couldn 't imagine any other sort of music for Silent Hill .
But this music also has its own , very individual internal rhythm ,
so I worked at synching the film to the music 's range ,
getting this floating feel .
The scene we 've just seen , with Radha Mitchell
driving down that road at the end of the day ,
with the girl drawing in the back seat ,
is , for me , a scene
which lets Akira Yamaoka 's music take over the film
and take over its rhythm .
The girl 's drawings , particularly the one of a sort of symbol ,
a cross on the top of a building , which we guess is religious ...
This is obviously the first clue , within the film ,
of this treasure hunt
which the heroine will have to follow
to get her daughter back .
On this level ,
the film slips into the mode of a video game ,
meaning that all through the film we 'll get these clues ,
some more subtle than others ,
some more coded than others ,
which will help her find her way
through the weird labyrinth that is Silent Hill .
It 's the moment when the film becomes more
the transcription of a game
than a story told in a traditional way .
I mentioned Rod Serling 's The Twilight Zone .
I think that another obvious influence , at least in this first part ,
is the series Alfred Hitchcock Presents ,
which I love .
This consisted , like the series The Twilight Zone ,
of tales with a twist ,
usually stories of wives
running away from home , of isolated people
in little towns ,
bumpkins confronted with certain problems ,
being chased by a policeman and so on .
Typical Hitchcock stories .
That was on my mind when I shot this scene ,
on the one hand because of Radha Mitchell 's " Grace Kelly " aspect ,
which really attracted me to her ,
and , on the other , by her action
of taking her daughter without telling her husband ,
whereby she ends up in this state of feeling guilty
that will cause her to make mistakes .
Also , when I shot this scene by the side of the road ,
in this little diner ,
I gave a lot of thought to the way
those series in the 1950s were filmed ,
with very simple , pure directing styles ,
with just ...
with very straightforward shots .
And this allowed me to get as quickly as possible
to the town of Silent Hill , with a narrative economy
which was exactly what I liked about that TV series .
This shot here
is a sort of " plane 's-eye view " of the countryside .
It represents , to me , the " map " in a video game .
For example , when you 're playing a role-playing game ,
there 's always a moment when your character 's in a map ,
when you see him moving through a scaled-down landscape ,
and you can get your bearings .
You see that there 's nothing around you ,
with maybe a town or evidence of civilisation
at the other end of the map ,
which you have to get to .
Hence that shot .
I also liked the fact that usually in American films
you 're always right at road level when a car 's moving .
The energy of the car always has to be very evident .
But I tried to distance myself ,
in an attempt to go on respecting that dreamlike aspect ,
that floating feeling , and to create the idea
that the car is tiny from the huge viewpoint we have ,
and that there 's no one , apparently , in the area she 's heading towards .
It 's dark and there 's no one in that landscape .
And the idea of solitude is clearly introduced for the first time
by that shot in the film .
Still trying to respect the aesthetics of those TV series
of the 1950s ,
I faked all of the car 's interior shots .
Practically all those shots were filmed the same day ,
using the so-called " poor man 's process " ,
where you shake the car .
I used a green screen ,
and then added all the backgrounds .
To inject a bit of realism into these shots ,
we digitally added dust on the windscreen ,
and mud splatters ,
creating a dirty look ,
which makes the special effects work very well , I think .
So it took the film 13 minutes
to get to Silent Hill .
From this moment on , the film is quite a faithful transcription
of the first game , which begins
with this accident that 's caused
by this mysterious apparition in the middle of the road .
If you 've watched the trailer carefully ,
you 'll have noticed
that you see the car literally pass through
the apparition in the road .
It was ghostlike .
I wanted to do away with that idea .
The trailer was finished before the film was fully edited .
But I found that idea a bit heavy-handed
and a bit too easy ,
like , " Oh , it was a ghost ! "
I wanted to be a bit more subtle than that .
On top of that , none of the shots I got from special effects
were very convincing ,
so I did away with that . And the accident works well as it is .
From this moment on , practically all the film was shot in the studio .
The real challenge of the film
was to have all its means geared to the art direction ,
to create a totally artificial universe ,
but which is nevertheless coherent
and of a completely unprecedented scale ,
working only in the studio .
Creating a virtual world ,
using processes that are , at times , very old-fashioned ,
and sometimes very modern , like digital imaging .
So that was the big , big challenge of the film .
In the game ...
It 's in the first game that we see these flakes falling through the fog .
Lots of fans have wondered if it 's snow .
But I 've always preferred to think of it as ash .
We 're in this dimension which could be that of purgatory ,
next to hell .
So the fires of hell are producing these ashes
which , cooled down , fall on the fog dimension .
It 's also explained by the history of the town ,
this mining town ,
whose underground mines are still on fire ,
which would explain the ash falling all over the town .
The shot of Radha entering the town ...
The version we 're seeing here , the video version ,
is more finished than what you 'd have seen in the cinema .
I finished the film a week before its American release .
A week before ,
we were still adding shots , special effects , to the film .
There were 800 VFX shots in the film .
We were doing all this at the last moment ,
and we couldn 't finished some shots , like that one there ,
which is improved in the video version .
The set of Silent Hill
is , in fact , a practically deserted neighbourhood
of a little town near Toronto .
When I showed photos of the game
to Carol Spier , the production designer ,
she said , " I know this place , "
and she took me to this deserted neighbourhood .
It was handy because hardly anyone lived there ,
and the whole place seemed to have stopped dead in 1965 .
All the buildings , the shops and so on ...
The whole place smelled of abandonment .
A major reason for filming in Toronto
is the fact of having found this amazing film set ,
which was our basis for the entry into Silent Hill .
These shots of her looking for her daughter in the streets ,
and then in this alley ,
are taken straight from the game .
It was important to me to transcribe
what I had felt in Silent Hill ,
a virtual place but which I knew intimately .
I knew every nook and cranny , having spent long hours there .
So I was obsessed with going back there in my film ,
and pinpointing all those places .
It was a sort of obsession with me .
One of the game 's strengths
is the famous siren ,
which announces the passing from one dimension to another .
The siren , to me , represents the success of the game ,
a game which , for many people , appeals to irrational fears ,
or to those of our collective memory ,
especially that siren which , of course ,
is a reference to air raids during the Second World War .
Maybe also to the sirens of concentration camps .
It 's a siren which suddenly makes the world
totally stress-full and dangerous ,
without your knowing exactly why .
This is one of the particulars of Silent Hill :
the horror in it is like a bad dream .
It 's not the sort of horror you usually get in films ,
making the audience jump
with the sudden appearances of people or cats in the frame ,
or the slamming of doors .
The fear in Silent Hill is much closer to ...
And this makes it much more fun , I think ...
It 's a fear that envelops you .
It 's something which chills our bones , without our knowing exactly why .
It 's an extremely complex approach to the fantastic ,
inasmuch as some people will be affected by this approach
and others will be left unmoved .
But for me this is the basis of the creation of Silent Hill .
It 's a game which , as well as being inspired by films ,
was also inspired by ...
by a passion of its creators ,
Akira Yamaoka , in particular , for modern art .
And there is , in Silent Hill , the game ,
a contemplative perspective ,
like watching from the sidelines , an atmosphere ,
whereby the point of view is slightly skewed ,
to create a sense of unease ,
and to suggest , in an almost insidious way ,
to things which affect us ,
like , of course , the idea of war or genocide ,
but never explicitly .
It 's something very particular , in a way ,
and this will make sure , I think , that the film
won 't become associated with other modern horror trends ,
which are all rather formatted . That 's why I 'm grateful
to the people of TriStar for letting me go in this direction ,
which I 'd call a more daring and complex direction
than the current one ,
which consists of going overboard with the gore ,
or of going overboard with the sudden , ghost-train surprises .
So this siren ,
for me , is the symbol of this Silent Hill-style fear .
The monsters in Silent Hill , apart from one sort , the cockroaches ...
But apart from the cockroaches ,
all the monsters were created the old-fashioned way .
I mean they were played by actors ,
mainly dancers wearing costumes .
Afterwards , I did a bit of digital make-up
on the monsters ' bodies .
The strange thing was that , after the trailer had come out ,
people said , " The monsters are digital . "
That surprised me because I really didn 't want
people to say that .
Digital technology is absolutely fantastic ,
and I love it .
At the same time , getting dancers to play the monsters ,
and using
their physical prowess
to create weird movements and so on ,
and making these monsters
by sculpting their costumes , as Patrick Tatopoulos did in this film ,
seems to me just as amazing .
It goes back to much more ancient traditions ,
it terms of forms of celebration
and theatricality .
Here , in fact , the Grey Children ...
That 's their name in the game .
The Grey Children are played
by a tiny woman dancer from the Far East ,
who specialises in buto ,
a very special Japanese choreographic art .
All those little creatures were played by her .
She was filmed over and over and the shots were assembled
in post-production .
But she played all the little monsters trying to grab Radha Mitchell .
Deep down , Silent Hill 's structure
is that of a fairy tale ,
with this idea of the character
getting lost in the forest and going to the witch 's house .
Yes , there 's been lots of psychoanalysis
of fairy tales ,
and the fact that they contain a mise en abyme
of our anxieties , our fears ...
It 's clear
that this is important for understanding Silent Hill .
It 's the pleasure of getting lost in the maze ,
of suddenly finding yourself without reference points .
It 's a feeling that I love and I seek it out .
Not just in films , but generally speaking ,
in all sorts of entertainment .
Obviously it 's something which requires , from the audience ,
a certain willing acceptance .
There are lots of people , even with horror films ,
who don 't want the films to go off the rails ,
who want them ruled by rational laws ,
with explanations for everything and so on .
My own tastes draw me to the opposite of that .
You have to drown in the atmosphere .
And I think that the allusions that there are in the game
to modern art
show how you can let yourself go like this .
Modern art is often put down
by people who aren 't willing to let themselves go .
It 's art which requires a certain willing abandon .
And to accept Silent Hill ,
my film and the game ,
you have to enjoy abandoning yourself to an atmosphere ,
you have to enjoy losing your footing ...
So the idea of the film was to constantly show this character
in a state of instability between several worlds .
She 's attacked by something in a sort of night-time ,
which fell very suddenly ,
then she wakes up , in the same place ,
this time in the fog , and so on .
I like the way Silent Hill burns its bridges as it goes .
I like this idea , very present in the game ,
that there 's no going back .
The deeper you dive into the dream ,
the more the bridges behind you collapse .
And this fascinates me ,
this idea of being driven ever forward .
Sometimes in the game
there were places where you had to walk and walk
for several minutes ,
and there was no going back .
Even if you wanted to ,
you 'd walked so far
that the idea of going back was exhausting .
This is unusual in a video game . They 're usually based on speed .
But Silent Hill had this way of taking you somewhere
and telling you , " There 's no way back . "
Here we have the first cut back to reality .
I really wanted you to feel the difference .
So I asked for really bright-coloured trucks .
I wanted you to realise how washed-out the colours had got ,
as we clearly pass back into a world that 's reality .
It 's almost Technicolor .
This is one of the scenes I added in later ,
slightly reluctantly ,
in order to give the audience
a male character to relate to .
And ... here you have him .
These are scenes
which are problematic for me , as I realised during the editing .
The whole film had been thought out so that Radha Mitchell 's character
experiences her adventure over several hours .
But the passages back to reality
forced me back to a world
of normal night and day .
This meant that the subjective time felt by the audience
was in fact dragged out .
As you could now see the father looking for his wife in the real world ,
over several days and nights ,
you understood that the film 's action took place over several days .
So this subjective time stretched out in people 's minds ,
which I think made the film
more contemplative . A problem .
I kept hoping during the editing
that TriStar would say , " The film 's too long .
" It needs cutting . "
My editor Sébastien Prangère and I had planned
to cut all of these scenes . We 'd done some tests and so on ...
We could have easily cut the scenes with Sean Bean .
The scenes in the main body of the film , not at the start or end .
In the end , to our great surprise ,
the people from TriStar never came to bother us ,
and the film was released as it was , the director 's cut ,
without our being asked to cut it and make it a length
that 's more normal . It 's 2 hours 7 minutes long .
It should have been more like 1 hour 50 , or 1 hour 45 .
The film is too long because of those unnecessary scenes .
Radha Mitchell was , as far as I was concerned ...
a choice
that was very particular in so much as ...
What I really liked about her
was her physique ,
which is a sort of blend of Mia Farrow and Grace Kelly .
She looks like someone
totally vulnerable ,
not a superhero , just ordinary ,
plunged into an extraordinary situation .
I really liked that about her .
Not to mention the fact
that she 's a very nice person .
Yet we didn 't have a fantastic relationship on the set .
I think that came from a basic problem
which was that Radha Mitchell , who was the studio 's choice ,
TriStar 's choice ,
rejected the film at first .
She read the script and said no .
In fact , she was waiting
to see how a film she 'd just made , Melinda and Melinda , would do .
This film , by Woody Allen , was a total flop ,
and she came back to us and said , " Yes , I 'll do Silent Hill . "
Due to her hesitation
our relationship didn 't get off to the best of starts .
It wasn 't that we hated each other
or anything like that .
In fact , I never had with her , nor she with me ,
the sort of complicity such a project required .
So it ended up being rather difficult between us .
I regret that , quite frankly .
She 's someone who 's very nice , very pleasant , in real life .
I wish the two of us had hit it off better .
But that 's often what happens with casting .
The audience don 't usually know , lucky for them ,
about all the false starts , the compromises
and problems involved in choosing actors ,
and the unfortunate psychological effects on a film set ,
seeing as we have to live very close to each other for a certain time .
So , when things don 't get off to the best start ,
it can cause problems , but that 's how it is .
So Sean Bean and Kim Coates , the police inspector ,
will be together for several scenes .
They 'd just worked together on The Island ,
by Michael Bay .
It 's a film I like a lot . It really impressed me .
And these actors are a lot of fun .
They act in loads of films every year .
It 's amazing how these guys just churn them out .
And they have their own sort of rhythm ,
their way of working and so on .
There 's no hesitation .
Sometimes it 's a bit disturbing , because they don 't question anything !
They just stand and wait for the camera to start rolling .
They 're members of the big troupe of regular film actors .
And they 're very nice people .
Laurie Holden , who plays Cybil ,
the policewoman ,
was someone I 'd noticed in The Majestic ,
the film with Jim Carrey ,
a film I loved ,
but which got absolutely slaughtered when it was released .
This poor film , which was about McCarthyism ,
had the bad luck to be released just after 9 / 11 .
So America , going through a phase of intense patriotism and solidarity ,
was confronted with this film about one of America 's darkest periods ,
so the film was shit on !
And Laurie Holden , who had the main female role ,
and who was very good ,
was in a way robbed of her springboard to success .
So I chose her for Silent Hill both because I thought she was good
in Darabont 's film ,
but also because I thought she had a Western-style attitude .
Her physique ...
Her slim hips give her a way of moving
that 's very " Western " , very masculine .
I thought she 'd be fantastic as a policewoman ,
in the tight leather trousers and so on .
And I think I was right . The character is pretty iconic .
But she 's an actress
who got really involved in the shooting of the film .
Even a little too much at times .
She 's under pressure the whole time she 's on the set .
She 's totally obsessed with ...
with being on the set ,
with getting completely in character and so on .
This sometimes caused problems with Radha Mitchell ,
who is slower to get going .
Radha Mitchell reaches cruising speed by the sixth take ,
whereas Laurie Holden is full-on in the first .
This made working with them both very complicated .
There were some tricky moments for me , when they weren 't in synch ,
because of their different ways of working .
So it was quite difficult , at times ,
to find an harmony on the set .
The Armless was played by a hip-hop dancer .
Every monster was played
by a dancer with a particular style .
He was totally blind inside that suit .
As were most of them .
They were all played by actors who had no way of seeing
any of the set around them .
So working with them was rather unusual .
It was very tough on them .
It was boiling hot on the sets . Especially this one .
This stretch of road had been re-created
in a big hangar , not a studio , so there was no air-conditioning .
And that , added to the chemical atmosphere
given off by the steam which made the fog ,
made it unbearable .
On top of which , that poor guy was wrapped up in his suit .
I think he must have suffered horribly .
So I 'm paying homage to him today .
Sometimes , when you 're writing these things ,
you don 't always realise what you 'll be inflicting on people .
This was an idea I was very pleased with .
In video games , of course , you can click onto a map ,
to find your bearings .
That 's not the case in a film , obviously ,
so I thought that , to find her way ,
the character would follow the bus stops .
It 's her way of finding her bearings .
It refers to something that happened to me .
I once got lost in Milan , Italy .
And to find my way I followed bus stops .
So that 's how I thought up
how she 'd find her way around at Silent Hill .
One thing that 's very important in Silent Hill ,
taken straight from the game ,
is that there are messages everywhere ,
things you have to read ,
to understand the story behind the story .
To understand where it is you 're going .
And in this school there are messages ,
clues all over the place ,
which give the audience hints about the past of Silent Hill .
Obviously , one of the things about video games
is that it 's risky to slow them down with explanations .
Game creators are reticent about doing that .
The way they envisage the narrative
is to leave it , to some extent , up to the player 's imagination .
The player plays ,
but thanks to these clues , phrases and notices
all over the place ,
is able to form an idea of the story behind the story .
That 's one of the most direct borrowings from the game .
It 's something you hardly ever get , I think , in films :
simply suggesting to the audience that ...
There 's something there to be understood ,
and they can either choose to understand it ,
or just pass it by and ignore that level of the film .
That was one of the things that was the most ...
the most radically inspired by video games , in the whole film ,
and the most risky , but I think it was worth a try ,
considering the importance of video-game culture today .
I thought it was interesting for a film to try
not just to adapt the obvious video-game stuff ,
the kinetic aspect , the aesthetics , the action ,
but also to try to get across
the weird narrative .
To invite that into a film and see what the result is .
I 'm not saying I achieved it , that it was a total success .
But I think it was worth trying it and saying ,
" We 're adapting a video game but it won 't be ... "
For most people , a video game is just people shooting at each other .
Speaking as someone who loves video games ,
I think video games have their own language .
And it interested me to introduce some of that language into a film .
This definition of Silent Hill as a mining town ,
which had suffered a catastrophe ,
with the mines igniting and making the town
impossible to live in ,
was a contribution of Roger Avary , the scriptwriter .
He was fascinated to hear about a mining town like this ,
which really exists but isn 't called Silent Hill , of course .
And he thought it was a neat way
of explaining why the town was in a sort of perpetual fog ,
with ash raining down .
As well as the symbolic dimension , he wanted this rational explanation ,
which I thought was a very good idea ,
that the town 's climate , its atmosphere ,
could be explained in several ways , including this one .
In the game there were silhouettes that came back regularly ,
the silhouettes of people in boiler suits .
They weren 't explained ,
and when we brought in this idea
that the town was a mining town built on a system of tunnels ,
it suddenly seemed obvious
to make these silhouettes in overalls miners .
We imagined that the people still living in Silent Hill
put these suits on
to go into the town and possibly confront the creatures
that jump on you when darkness falls .
The heroine has just run over a hopscotch game ,
with " heaven " and " hell " written
in the squares at either end .
It 's typical of this idea of the fantastic ,
that everything that 's evil or diabolical
lurks around the world of childhood ,
and that what looks like a game is the sign of an evil power ,
which first and foremost attacks the purity of childhood .
It 's something that you find
in American horror and fantasy , which is in essence Puritan ,
and in Japanese horror and fantasy ,
which takes great pains to define purity .
And the purity of children
is an undeniable source for Japanese horror and fantasy .
And I think this is one of the bridges
between these two folk traditions of envisaging the fantastic .
Here again , we 're back to following clues .
These signs which help the heroine understand things .
Here , it 's a child 's handmarks in the dust on a desk .
That 's typical of the way video games work .
You walk into an empty room , with nothing apparently happening ,
and you have to find the clue
which will let you progress to the next stage .
The chase in the school
is one of the very rare references to a famous film .
I was a bit annoyed with myself for doing it , but I couldn 't help it .
It 's one of my favourite films .
It 's borrowed from a scene in a film by Mario Bava : Operazione paura ,
or Kill , Baby ... Kill ! .
One of my favourite horror and fantasy directors , Mario Bava ,
an Italian director of the 60s ,
who really favoured this sort of atmosphere ,
of decomposition and ...
empty buildings with a glorious past ,
but which have now been corrupted by the damp and by time .
For a horror and fantasy style it 's almost literary , melancholic ...
It 's melancholic the way the film takes us through these places ,
which have known their share of joy , but of tragedy too ,
but which are now just empty shells ,
inhabited by shadows , the shadows of the past .
That 's quite an old definition of the fantastic ,
a romantic definition .
And I think that the film
clearly tries to have that mood .
In this scene , originally ,
there was nothing in the last cubicle .
You just heard the girl crying and then the heroine ...
opened the cubicle door and there was nothing .
That was the surprise .
Then I thought , " It 's a shame there 's nothing ! "
And as we went on ,
I imagined a creature that isn 't in the game ,
a creature I designed pretty quickly ,
a creature which also refers
to a very popular culture in Japan ,
which is that of bondage , of sado-masochism .
So I imagined this creature , tortured with barbed wire ,
twisted into an impossible position , which then goes after the heroine .
First it seems to be a body , then it 's a creature , which haunts ...
these toilets .
It 's a creature that was created at the last minute , if you like .
It was on the set that we thought it up .
It was the film 's choreographer ,
who worked with all the dancers who played the monsters ,
who played this monster .
As well as playing Red Pyramid , he also played this creature .
His name 's Roberto Campanella .
And he 's largely responsible for the success of the film 's creatures .
The writing above the body suggests
- and this makes it more horrible -
that the torture inflicted on this man
was done in the spirit of a children 's game .
Here we 're getting to the core
of the definition of the town Silent Hill ,
which is that it 's a tormented , tortured place .
The reality of this little town
has been , in a way , tortured
by a child .
Like a little girl using a lighter to melt her doll .
Well ,
the character of Alessa has done the same to an entire town ,
held a flame to it , in a way .
The whole film displays the signs of this torment .
What I like about this idea
is that the body of the town isn 't so much symbolised by its inhabitants ,
as by its architecture .
It 's the idea
that the town has a real living body ,
that this body is the buildings , the alleyways and so on ,
and that these places can be tortured
just like a body of flesh and bone can be .
It 's an idea that 's found , obviously , in modern art ,
an idea that 's been worked on a lot , that the appearances around us
can be , in a way , damaged and torn to shreds
by the artist .
And to me , Alessa
- and this is something I felt deeply when playing the game -
is an artist , a tormented artist ,
who , in a way , imposes her torture on reality .
Not just on the people living in this town ,
but also on its entire environment .
To me , that 's a fascinating and more or less unique idea .
This scene illustrates what I was saying
about this spirit which , in a way , haunts Silent Hill ,
which tortures the surroundings like you 'd torture a body .
It was BUF , the famous French visual effects studio ,
which did the scenes where the town undergoes these transformations .
We spent a lot of time
discussing the process , and getting an effect whereby the ...
the decor is transformed like flesh that 's being burnt ,
with a flame held to it .
I think the result is quite amazing .
This idea wasn 't explored so much in the game ,
where the character usually fainted and woke up in another world .
Here I wanted this effect of decrepitude ,
which is very particular ,
underscored by very organic sounds , created by Nicolas Becker ,
our sound designer ,
to get this effect of the decor suddenly becoming
like an orifice , an orifice of flesh subjected to fire .
It 's an idea of torture ,
which will , later in the film ,
be directly applied to one of the characters .
The shots you see in the film , from unusual angles or positions ,
were made possible
because a lot of the sets were totally constructed .
They were not only built in the studio ,
but to some extent they were designed
to let the camera get shots at angles I 'd envisaged
on the storyboards .
So a lot of the sets were detachable ,
a lot of the elements of the sets were specially worked
to make certain shots possible .
One of the film 's complexities
was that the angles were so specific
that we were at times forced to film
in a dislocated way ,
doing one angle , another and another , until we got a complete scene .
That 's very complicated ,
and it made everyone on the production very tense .
especially the producer , a Canadian called Don Carmody .
This way of filming made him very tense .
He was used to being on the sets of B movies ,
and movies which get filmed quite straightforwardly ,
and the fact that this film was so complicated and precise
made him rather tense .
Here we see the first encounter
between Radha Mitchell and ...
the Alessa character ,
who 's the double , the original , of her daughter ,
and therefore the brains
behind the mystery of Silent Hill .
In fact , we 're in her head .
She 's drawing what we can see happening .
The idea is that she wildly scribbles a drawing
in the same way as she tortures the decor .
It 's a massacre with crayons .
So the idea , at this point ,
is that we not only see the decor , but its architect too .
And the architect , as it happens , is this little girl .
I think this sequence in the school is the most spectacular in the film
and closest to the game .
If the people listening have never played the game ,
this will give them a good idea of its rather special atmosphere ,
which made it famous , even though it didn 't sell much .
I was surprised to see the sales figures for France ,
which were only in their hundreds .
It 's a very particular game .
It 's very hard to tolerate
an atmosphere like this for hours on end .
And few people try .
The game has a huge reputation , even outside gaming circles ,
but if you do your sums , few have actually played it .
Odd !
This scene in the school playground
introduces one of the most emblematic characters
in the history of video games ,
the Red Pyramid character ,
this sort of executioner .
I think he looks like one of those penitents ...
those penitents in black
that you got in Spain ,
linked to the history of the Inquisition and so on .
In the game he 's an executioner ,
linked to the male character
of the second game , Silent Hill 2 .
Here , the wife brushes by her husband in a parallel dimension ,
and this shows us how the universe of Silent Hill works ,
by the superimposition of parallel dimensions .
It 's my favourite scene of all those with Sean Bean ,
the husband .
And it 's true that this scene
allowed us to say
that the scenes with Sean Bean were useful to the film .
It is a nice sequence ,
with a clear reference to the myth of Orpheus ,
which was given a film treatment by Jean Cocteau .
But was it worth slowing down the whole film just for this scene ?
I don 't know . But by itself the scene works very well .
In the game the cockroaches weren 't that great .
They 'd swarm round your feet and nibble at you ,
reducing your life bar .
They had no more function than that ,
they just increased the stress
for the player .
We tried to give them a bit more personality ,
making them a living mass , like a marabunta ,
a column of soldier ants which eats everything in its path .
But also , in this passage ,
we discover that these cockroaches
used to be human beings .
They are some of the lost souls
stuck in the hell of Silent Hill .
The two heroines are stuck in the boiler room ,
where they 'll be attacked by Red Pyramid ,
who 's going to pierce the door with his huge sword .
And this is one of the many scenes
in which the film tackles the idea of rape .
Rape inflicted directly on the set .
This place where the two women have holed up ,
and the way in which it is split open
by Red Pyramid 's enormous sword ...
This is a way of inflicting on the decor something ...
which , of course , would usually be inflicted on a human body .
This idea recurs regularly in the film ,
the idea that ...
the set suffers the abuse on behalf of the characters .
I like the idea
that the ' roaches are like the sperm here ,
pouring in through the broken door
and invading the room .
I think it 's all part ...
of what creates the unease , of course , in this universe .
But it 's also a symbolic interpretation ,
which you find in all modern art ,
this way of transcribing anxieties and unpleasant things
by playing around with the symbols .
It 's something I tried to keep in mind .
Maybe it 's one reason why the film
didn 't take a real hammering from the censors .
We expected the film
to be given an 18 rating in England , a 16 in France ...
But the film got past all the censors without any real problem .
I think that it 's so overtly symbolic
that , in the end , the censors had nothing to say .
Everything 's a matter of interpretation ,
so it was easy to not understand .
I think this is one reason the film was spared
what happens to a lot of horror films nowadays ,
getting unjustly banned .
This is one of the most precise visions
of what happens when you pass from one dimension to another .
The ash
and the debris of one dimension
form the skin of another .
I like the way the BUF technicians did this .
They gave it a very Jean Cocteau aspect .
The world takes shape again
as if it had been filmed and the film run backwards .
The pieces of reality stick together again
like film running backwards .
I think it 's a lovely idea ,
which works very well in this world .
This part here ... We 're exactly halfway through the film ,
and it 's the moment where the film leaves
the very simple narrative
of the video game , following clues ,
to embark on a more complex narrative
which tries to explain what really happened at Silent Hill .
So now we get the intervention of other characters ,
and we 're going to discover the key to the story .
This was a risky thing to do .
I still wonder whether it was the right thing to do .
Couldn 't I have tried to keep the film going
in the almost abstract manner of the first half ,
and not give a more conventional structure to the second ?
But would they have let me make such a film ?
These are questions I 'll never have answers to .
But I still wonder whether it was a good thing to do ,
to make the second half more classic ,
and to bring in so many characters .
This little scene with Sean Bean in his car
was shot during the re-shooting of the film .
We finished the film , edited it ,
and then , several months later , we did the re-shooting .
This scene replaces a clumsier one ,
which took place in the town library ,
where the character looked for clues about what had happened at Silent Hill .
We 'd imagined
that he would break ...
that he 'd break into the library at night
and consult the documentation himself .
That 's just one of the little things we changed
between the original shooting and the final result .
The film was shot in an extremely short timeframe ,
in 61 days , to be precise .
That 's quite short when you consider
that there are over 110 different sets in the film .
So some days I had to shoot three sets in the day .
That was complicated .
One in the morning , one in the afternoon , OK ,
but when you have to do three sets , three different scenes ,
with people changing ,
the lighting to set up and so on , it 's complicated .
This explains the film 's style , to some extent .
It 's different from Brotherhood of the Wolf ,
with fewer shots ,
the shots are more streamlined ,
and try to encompass the set immediately .
The film was quite hard to make because of this schedule , but ...
At the same time ,
its budget was more than comfortable for a horror film .
Forty million dollars .
But , obviously , what we spent on the sets ,
on the sumptuous sets ,
we had to make up on the shooting time .
That was the compromise ,
and I decided not to save on the visuals ,
and to make it in the time allotted , which wasn 't always easy .
This scene was shot in an extraordinary location ,
which used to be a hotel ,
and was abandoned ...
Abandoned to the rats , to squatters ,
to all sorts of insects ...
It was a truly sumptuous location for our purposes .
It was a piece of Silent Hill we found , but real .
We didn 't add many props .
It 's the place pretty much as it was .
This caused a problem
because the dust that was in this ...
in this location
was quite toxic .
We had it analysed and it contained spores ...
of a sort of mould or fungus ,
which could cause serious allergic attacks if breathed in .
There were also pigeon droppings ...
The building was full of pigeons .
Rats and so on .
All of this together made quite an explosive mixture .
So , in order to be able to shoot in this building ,
we had to spray a sort of glue ,
which kept the dust stuck to the ground .
Because , of course , the technicians ' union
said we couldn 't work in such an unhealthy place ,
so we reached
a sort of compromise ,
by glueing the dust ,
spraying this thin skin of glue over everything ,
so that we could film in there without kicking up the dust .
That 's how we managed it .
For a while it looked unlikely because of those health concerns .
The scenes with Sean Bean were deliberately shot like a film noir .
That was intentional .
The atmosphere you get in American movies of the 1940s .
The bricks , the rain , the empty buildings ,
the wet trenchcoat and so on ...
I thought Sean Bean 's face really looked the part .
Sometimes it takes a lot of effort to create a film noir feeling ,
with lots of props ... But I think it 's interesting
that film noir , a major genre in the history of cinema ,
but a risky one to reference ,
can be evoked by just a face .
And I think Sean Bean 's face lends itself to this transcription .
It has that film noir essence .
I tried something risky here ,
by giving the film two levels of understanding .
There 's what Radha Mitchell comes to understand ,
investigating inside Silent Hill ,
and there 's what the father works out ,
investigating outside Silent Hill .
I wanted to see how the two interpretations could come together .
This is sort of what I tried to do
when I was asked to add scenes with Sean Bean :
to suggest several interpretations .
This was quite difficult to do .
In fact ,
as the film is already giving the audience plenty to interpret ,
maybe it was quite a risky thing to attempt .
But I was swept along
by the idea that this aspect ...
People are used to this aspect ,
because it 's something you find in series like The X-Files ,
or , more recently than that , in Lost .
I mean that each character represents one viewpoint ,
one interpretation , about what 's going on .
You don 't give a direct explanation of the supernatural ,
or of these incredible events ,
but there are as many interpretations as there are viewpoints
represented by the characters .
And this encouraged me in thinking that it could work .
It 's what made The X-Files and Lost so popular .
Here 's another illustration of what I call the labyrinth theme
within Silent Hill ,
the idea that each decor hides another ,
that each decor is in fact concealing another decor ,
and that the more keys you find to go through these layers ,
the more you descend inside yourself .
This is something
that 's really fascinating about how video games work ,
the idea that the labyrinth doesn 't only represent
the game 's arithmetic architecture ,
but also the player 's psyche .
A film that puts across this labyrinth idea really well ,
this idea of a place where everything 's about codes ,
about signs and numbers to be deciphered ,
is a film that 's become more and more famous with time ,
Dario Argento 's Suspiria ,
which established this sort of arithmetic architecture ,
using the environment of a dance academy ,
and did so
by giving this absolutely monstrous dimension to the sets .
I 've never hidden the fact that Dario Argento
was a big influence on me ,
not just in making me want to make films ,
but also in defining my own style .
That way in which he always represented
the " beauty " of horror , if I can put it like that ,
realising that horror isn 't just a situation , but an atmosphere ,
sometimes a whole world folding over you ,
and with him this was extremely sensual .
His main characters are often heroines ,
pursuing occult secrets ,
secrets often related to witches or evil influences in this world ,
where the demonology refers directly to politics or sociology .
All of this means that there 's a link ,
by no means a hidden one ,
between Silent Hill and Dario Argento .
But I think that to some extent the people who made Silent Hill
are fans of films like Suspiria .
All of that , I think , gets mixed up
in the way they conceive of demonology ,
as it is understood by folk traditions of the West ,
and which was very well illustrated by Dario .
The incinerated sacrificial chamber
was the worst set we had to shoot in on this film .
All the burnt bits of the set were real burnt planks ,
taken from burnt buildings and so on .
It was very hot . We were under big windows ,
which you see in one of the low-angle shots .
As well as that , the fumes from the burnt wood , the charcoal ,
made the atmosphere unbearable .
The shooting was very unpleasant .
We also had the nasty surprise that one of the reels was scratched ,
so we had to shoot again .
It was the place we filmed in which most made me
want to get the hell out of there !
This is one of the most interesting things about this scene ,
that the character has to jump , like in a platform game ,
from one piece of metal to another , above an abyss .
And Radha Mitchell insisted on doing her own stunts in this scene .
Obviously , she had a safety cable on ,
like circus acrobats , but she did the stunts ,
jumping from one metal beam to the next .
This just shows that her approach to acting
has nothing abstract about it .
She likes playing real-life characters
confronted with real problems .
I think this is why , at first , she wasn 't keen to make this film ,
which is structurally very abstract .
I think she 's someone who needs real things around her ,
who needs to do real things .
I recently saw a good film with her in , Rogue ,
by Greg McLean , with a gigantic crocodile .
She plays a guide in the Australian outback ,
who faces this monster .
And she 's great in the film ,
because she 's acting in situations that are very clearly defined .
She 's one of these actors who need to attach themselves to something real ,
in order to function .
In this scene , Radha Mitchell
is confronted with an incarnation of Alessa ,
who takes the appearance of a little " Italian-style " ghost ,
with this baroque aspect ,
the rotting uniform , the strange face and so on .
People say ,
" Oh , that 's a reference to modern Japanese ghost films . "
What they call J-Horror . But it 's not at all .
I love J-Horror , and especially Ring ,
the Japanese original ,
my favourite horror and fantasy film , along with The Others of Amenábar
of the last ten years .
It 's not a reference to J-Horror ,
it 's a reference to the little ghosts
in Italian horror and fantasy ,
especially in Bava 's Kill Baby ... Kill ! , which I mentioned earlier ,
but also in Fellini 's sketch , Toby Dammit ,
in Spirits of the Dead ,
an important film .
And I particularly liked Fellini 's section in the film .
It 's more a reference to that , and not at all to J-Horror .
It 's quite amusing
that after this , Laurie Holden was in The Mist ,
a film by Frank Darabont
all about a mist that envelops a little town ,
bringing monsters with it .
It 's quite amusing
to see how , quite often , actors get typecast
in films which tackle similar sorts of themes .
What 's more , Sean Bean made a film called The Dark , in Canada ,
a film with certain similarities ,
because it 's about a couple , he and Maria Bello ,
looking for their daughter .
So it 's quite interesting to see these actors
cast , in a way , by different directors ,
to play roles in worlds where the themes have similarities .
This amazing church at the top of the stairs
is a building that really exists .
It 's a Masonic building , which I found in the suburbs ...
in the suburbs of a town
quite close to Toronto .
This building fascinated me because I really like
its fortress aspect , its sanctuary aspect ,
this idea of trying to protect oneself against the outside ,
which is typical of the architecture
of this location .
It interested me to use it . So we filmed the real building
and constantly incorporated shots of it
within the film of the studio set ,
which was just the steps . We only built the steps ,
and a bit of the entrance .
The rest isn 't a digital image ,
it 's a real building , filmed separately ,
and added to the image .
It was risky , suddenly introducing all these people into a place
which had seemed up until that point to be deserted .
The idea is that this is the last group of inhabitants ,
and that when the siren sounds ,
they come and take sanctuary here ,
which is the only place
that the creatures released by Alessa can 't enter .
This was , obviously , a risk .
I discussed this at length with Akira Yamaoka .
For him , anything that could develop or enrich the mythology of Silent Hill
was welcome , as long as it fitted in with the original premise .
At the time , Akira Yamaoka was looking
for ideas for the next Silent Hill .
Silent Hill 4 had been released
but the fans hadn 't liked it .
I love Silent Hill 4 : The Room .
But it wasn 't liked , I think ,
because it moved too far from the original concept .
So Akira Yamaoka wanted to get back to the original concept ,
while enriching it with stuff about the town 's history .
And everything we were doing in the film
really interested him .
He took notes and so on .
I think that , in a way , it helped fertilise his imagination ,
and gave him a direction to go in with the next game .
Nothing came of it in the end because ,
to my great personal disappointment ...
the game Silent Hill was taken away from its Japanese creators
and given to an American team ,
who made Silent Hill 5 .
So it 's no longer the Japanese
making the Silent Hill games .
Personally , maybe because I 'm a director and scriptwriter ,
I 'd have preferred it
if the original team was still involved with future Silent Hill games .
The inside of the church was totally rebuilt in the studio .
It was a very impressive set ,
and a bit intimidating .
It was going to be bigger !
But we decided , for budgetary reasons ,
to make it a bit smaller than planned .
That was the right course to take because its scale caused me problems .
Especially during the final scene .
So it 's a set
that was very impressive , and ...
And it shows
the epic and theatrical aspect of Carol Spier 's talent .
That was one of the reasons I chose
this production designer , the fact that there 's
an epic and theatrical scale to what she does .
She 's not just a talented set decorator .
There is always something larger than life
in her work ,
something incredibly huge and epic .
I chose Alice Krige to play the big baddy , Christabella ,
because I love her as an actress .
I particularly like her in the films
of the Quay brothers .
She made a film I really liked called Institute Benjamenta .
She was amazing .
And I remembered her , of course , as the ghost in Ghost Story ,
which was quite an interesting film .
She 's an actress
with a great reputation . She 's very professional .
She does a lot of theatre , and she was just perfect
to play Christabella ,
because she 's so imposing .
She imposed her character on all the other actors
that we chose to play the members of her sect .
A very imposing manner .
She was admired on the set ,
both by the crew and by those acting around her .
This sequence , passing from the sect praying in the church ,
to the children praying ,
was a way for me to defuse the tension of the film ,
showing what I think is bad religion ,
and what is " good " religion , practised in a decent way .
So you get the intolerance of the sect ,
juxtaposed with the children praying , which for me
is a comforting vision of religion .
Seeing these scenes reminds me
that part of the style of Silent Hill , of this film ,
I discovered , or elaborated ,
while I was co-producing a film
called House of Voices , by Pascal Laugier ,
which is a film with lots of similar themes .
It was really interesting , watching Pascal directing .
He 's an immensely talented young director .
So I watched him directing and working with this sort of imagery
at the time I was working on ... or when Silent Hill was on my mind ,
and I think there 's a sort of dialogue between the two films .
There 's something similar about the way
in which the religious environment is depicted ,
in the interests of a ghost story ,
a ghost story originating in a character 's mind .
So there are plenty of points in common ,
as there are with his new film , Martyrs .
For example , there 's the image of the woman in the cellar ,
tortured with the steel helmet ,
which could bring to mind the image
of the janitor in the Silent Hill school .
The two of us are very close , we 're good friends ,
we both talk a lot about the cinema of the fantastic ,
and besides producing his film , what mainly interested me
was helping him get started
because I was convinced of his talent .
And I think that , without his knowing it ,
the way he made House of Voices had a big influence on me and Silent Hill .
The paradox with the church scenes
was that the set was huge , absolutely enormous ,
but the scenes had to be shot , paradoxically , very quickly .
All the scenes in the church took very little time , in fact .
I think that , in all , they took four or five days .
Only a day and a half was put by for the final scene in the church .
That was mostly due to the work schedule .
All the church scenes were left until the end ,
so whenever any cutting back was done , it cut into the big final scenes .
It was a bit of a gamble on my part , thinking ,
" If I leave the big scenes till last , they won 't dare stop me . "
But the problem , in fact ,
was that the insurance on the film ,
the completion bond ,
meant that people were sent to make sure it finished on time , in 61 days .
And their arrival
forced us to film the church scenes very quickly ,
and even changing the end .
The end we 'd planned wasn 't what we finally filmed .
That 's all part of filmmaking nowadays ,
the fact that the ...
the insurance agents have all the power ,
if ever you happen to overrun your schedule .
They already had me in their sights , anyway ,
because they 'd heard of how Brotherhood of the Wolf had overrun ,
mostly because of weather problems
and outside shooting ,
but as far as they were concerned
I was a somewhat " dangerous " director .
So they paid particular attention to the way I filmed Silent Hill .
In a way , they forced me to make the film on schedule ,
which was good , really , because it was so complicated to make
that I couldn 't have endured another day on the set .
In any case , the completion bond people went home ,
totally reassured about my ability to finish a film on schedule .
That phrase , " A mother is God in the eyes of her child , "
is , if I can put it like this , the cure for the sickness ,
in this film .
As far as I 'm concerned ,
you can 't make a noir film without giving some hint
of where there might be light , where the end of the tunnel is .
And that phrase , for me ,
is that hint .
It effectively demonstrates my conception of " good "
in this film ,
which is otherwise very dark , gloomy and depressing , perhaps .
What I was trying to say was ,
" If there 's a cure for all this despair , then that is it .
" That 's how you should interpret the film . "
I 've always thought that films which are totally dark ,
with no spark of light ,
are films which , even if excellent ,
are in some way condemned to not being understood ,
condemned to remain in obscurity ,
in the obscurity which they themselves created .
It 's always risky not to give people a way out .
When you 're a director - this is how I see it -
one of your responsibilities
is to show where the exit is
from a world that is so radically unpleasant .
This map is directly inspired by the maps in the game Silent Hill .
They look like this , and when you 're lost
you can get your bearings , more or less , by following ...
by going and looking at these maps .
So it amused me to reproduce them in a hospital ,
where you do get such guides to help you find your way
through the maze of huge administrative buildings .
When Dan Laustsen and I did the screen tests ,
we realised that there were distinct ways of filming Radha Mitchell
and Laurie Holden .
Radha Mitchell , for example ,
needed a slightly high-angle shot with a short lens ,
whereas it was better to shoot Laurie Holden
from a low-angle shot , with a long focal length .
Their two faces ' structures were so distinct
that we had to keep changing lens to shoot one or the other .
And this scene is typical
of the way we worked on their faces .
So I used a bit of a Kubrick style to shoot Radha Mitchell ,
always this slightly high-angle shot to bring out her forehead ,
whereas with Laurie Holden
we 're always at a low angle , with her face raised .
This fight scene with Laurie Holden ...
As I said before , she 's an actress
who gives it everything she 's got , right from take one .
In this scene she really does fight .
She really does land those blows !
Those guys have iron helmets ,
and she really is hitting them .
When you see a guy go flying , it 's because she whacked him .
So much so , in fact , that she had to go to hospital
because she 'd badly hurt her hand .
And when we came to finish the scene ,
we had to be careful she didn 't do it again .
That 's typical of her , going all out .
It isn 't an action film .
It 's the only film I 've made with hardly any action scenes .
When I start a new project ,
I try to make it anti what I did before .
So Brotherhood of the Wolf was anti Crying Freeman ,
and Silent Hill was anti Brotherhood of the Wolf .
I try to muddy the waters .
People expect this , so I 'll do that .
People expect slo-mo , action scenes , kung-fu and so on .
Well , this 'll be different !
I always try
to play with people 's expectations ,
not just to confound those
who want to put me in a neatly labelled box .
I 'm just constantly trying to be a little bit surprising .
So I deliberately made Silent Hill
with only one bit of slo-mo in the whole film ,
and hardly any action scenes ,
to make people say , " He didn 't do what he usually does ! "
It 's always a bit too easy , I personally think ,
to reduce a director to his trademark gimmicks and so on .
And I think it 's fun for a director to go against that .
This scene of the beating was shot by my 2nd-unit director , Bill Gereghty ,
who 'd worked with me on Crying Freeman and Brotherhood of the Wolf .
Bill used to be an assistant to Sam Peckinpah ,
and when he had to do this scene he asked me , " How do you want it ? "
And I said , " Like in a Western , of course ! "
I think when he shot the scene ,
he must have had in mind Clint Eastwood in A Fistful of Dollars .
The way he shot Laurie Holden getting beaten up must come from that .
The Nurses ...
There are swarms of these creatures in Silent Hill ,
and they 're very specific to the game .
The fans literally adore them ,
and I understand why ,
because they 're a combination of horror
and an extremely sexy attitude ,
an eroticism that is in no way concealed .
Doing the Nurses was complicated ,
precisely because they are such emblematic creatures ,
and because they move around in gangs .
So we had to organise an enormous casting call
of lap dancers ,
because they had the best combination
of the requisite physical and aesthetic qualities .
The choreographer
was very excited about doing a chorus line ,
with all the dancers lined up like that , in the film .
And what started out as quite a weird choreography
practically became a mechanical ballet .
There was a risk there ,
since they were going to dance rather than move .
Would it look like Michael Jackson 's Thriller ?
That was my fear when we were shooting .
It is a bit like that .
In any case , it 's a very strange sequence .
I wanted to make it closer in mood to the ballet Ophelia ,
and The Tales of Hoffmann ,
which are full of characters like clockwork dolls ,
with jerky movements and so on .
That 's how I wanted to approach the scene .
The technique I came up with
to create Silent Hill 's monsters
was a combination of ...
sculpture ,
meaning a full costume sculpted by Patrick Tatopoulos ,
a dancer inside it ,
and special effects
to create ruptures within the physical rhythms .
We made it so that there 's a variation in the speeds ,
to constantly create a kind of fragmented movement ,
to create something that 's both harmonious
but also strange and even unpleasant to watch .
Another essential part of the monsters is the sound .
This was worked on , with his usual care ,
by Nicolas Becker , a great French sound designer .
He did Brotherhood of the Wolf ,
but also a magnificent recent sci-fi film called Sunshine .
He 's a true artist of sound .
His particularity is that he works with natural sounds .
They often end up sounding very strange ,
but they 're not synthetic , not created on a synthesiser ,
they come from real sounds .
He goes and records sounds in factories ,
at huge reservoirs ...
He records the deaf and dumb , he records people and ...
He gets specific sounds but doesn 't doctor them .
That 's something about him which I really admire .
It 's also one reason
why Silent Hill 's monsters have this organic feel .
The sound isn 't doctored , it isn 't artificial ,
it 's a sound which is , in a way , surrealist ,
which was removed from somewhere else and stuck here .
It 's out of place .
Working with him is always a great pleasure .
Here , the character is faced with the truth ,
in the form of a blinding light
and a voice telling her she 's won .
So that 's another direct reference to the way video games work .
I think this scene serves a similar purpose
to the one in The Matrix ,
where Neo meets the architect .
What I mean is that
it 's the moment when the character meets her creator ,
in the spirit of Pirandello : an endless reflection .
It 's the idea that , at a certain point ,
the fictional character
meets the person who put her in this often uncomfortable situation .
This is interesting
because my film has quite a few things in common with The Matrix .
Both films were produced by Andrew Mason ,
who was a producer on The Matrix ,
but also on Dark City and The Crow ,
which are films that work in a similar way to Silent Hill .
I 'd almost call them " brain " films ,
films where the world is created in the imagination of a character ,
whom you finally meet .
The flashback sequence wasn 't intended to be like this .
It was going to look like a 20th Century Fox film from 1960 ,
produced by Darryl Zanuck .
I 'd planned to have saturated colours , to shoot it in Cinemascope ,
with that excessively stylised quality
that you got in 1960s Fox melodramas ,
which I love .
But it turned out
that to do it like that would cost far too much money ,
there 'd be too many pieces missing and so on .
My editor Sébastien Prangère and I
wondered how we could change tack and make this flashback
without the missing pieces being evident .
Then I thought that we could do it
with a treatment like in Depeche Mode videos ,
doing the exact opposite of what we 'd originally intended .
Rather than make a big Fox melodrama ,
we 'd do it like something shot in Super 8 by Anton Corbjin ,
something very grainy ,
like an old home movie with bits missing .
It was someone who 'd worked with me on the menus of the HK collection
- the collection of Asian films that I edit -
who totally created the look of this flashback .
His name is Kook Ewo , and he still works with me .
The concept was to go back through all the places
that we 'd visited in this adventure ,
and to give an explanation
why these places were so important to Alessa ,
how these places had been the theatre of her endless suffering ,
the pain of a little girl unluckily born to an adulteress ,
in a sect .
And who therefore paid for her mother 's sins .
The torture scene was obviously hard to imagine
inasmuch as the torture of a child
is something that today is totally taboo .
It 's a real taboo .
So we wondered for a long time how we 'd portray that .
Originally , the scene was much more explicit .
But I think it was a good decision
to leave part of it to the viewer 's imagination .
In the game it 's obvious that Alessa was tortured
by the inhabitants of Silent Hill ,
during some sort of diabolical ritual .
So there 's a sort of reversal of the idea
of Alessa getting tortured by a sect of fanatics ,
so that the sect ends up paying dearly ,
because Alessa , following her martyrdom , becomes ...
a spirit , a superior power , an entity ,
who will degree severe punishment upon them all .
This scene has a reference to a famous character in the game ,
a cult character called Lisa Garland ,
also known as the Red Nurse .
This was a little nod and wink to the fans ,
putting Lisa Garland in this scene and explaining why
she 's stuck in Silent Hill , as she 's just a nurse .
But she does commit a sin , from Alessa 's point of view ,
with her unhealthy curiosity ,
going and peeking at her .
And this is what damns her .
This is where , I think , the film gets a bit complicated
for those who only want to decipher it
from a Judaeo-Christian conception of good and evil .
In this scene you can understand that Alessa , in her martyrdom ,
is visited by the devil ,
who offers her the chance of vengeance .
In fact , from what I know of Japanese folk traditions ,
which I believe inspired the game to a large extent ,
I think that what 's really happening in this scene
is that Alessa is visited by her double .
In her pain she 's been split into several Alessas .
There 's the real Alessa , suffering ,
there 's the evil Alessa , her dark side , who 's just visited her ,
and there 's a good Alessa ,
who 's made safe in the real world in the shape of Sharon ,
the little girl adopted by Sean Bean and Radha Mitchell .
I think that 's the explanation
for how she becomes a multi-faceted character ,
with different faces and different ages .
It 's something that 's in the game , which intrigues players :
why Alessa exists in different guises , at different ages ...
Both evil guises
and guises that are ... " human " .
I think that 's the explanation .
In Far-Eastern religions ,
good and evil aren 't exterior to us .
We contain our own good and our own evil .
We are our own god and our own devil .
I think this is the explanation for what 's happening here in the film .
Alessa splits into several Alessas .
That was a very Japanese idea .
The moment Alessa makes her pact with her evil double ,
it creates a sort of nuclear fission .
The hospital bed is the heart of the nuclear reactor ,
and everything around it is sort of contaminated ...
by the fission .
It 's an idea which ...
We know that , because of Hiroshima and Nagasaki ,
the Japanese have a deep fear of the atom bomb ,
nuclear radiation and so on .
And I think that this is part of Silent Hill :
the apocalyptic landscape and the ash raining down ,
like the ash that rained on Hiroshima and Nagasaki after they were bombed .
All this makes sense , I think .
I mean that this whole universe like a concentration camp ,
with its sirens sounding the alarm , with its barbed wire ,
recalls not only World War II 's concentration camps ,
but also the nuclear bombs dropped by America
on Japan at the end of the war .
I think it all intersects .
As I 've already said ,
one ambition of modern art has always been
to transcribe the century 's great fears ,
unlike sacred art ,
which transcribed beauty
and the elevation of spirit this procured .
Here , I think that ...
within this idea
I 've tried to incorporate the idea
that Alessa 's hospital bed
is the heart of the nuclear reactor of all that 's happened .
This scene shows how mature Jodelle Ferland is .
Her lines were very complicated ,
full of biblical references , very symbolic and so on .
And the way this little girl took charge of her lines
and made something of them
was , in my opinion , very special .
I think Jodelle Ferland is a gifted child .
I think that a part of the strangeness she radiates
comes from the fact that she 's gifted , in a real sense .
I mean that she 's someone who , in a child 's body ,
has a superior mind .
I think this made her imposing .
At the same time , she tried to be the little girl we wanted to see .
But deep down she 's a much sharper person ,
much more precise .
It was always interesting to catch the real Jodelle Ferland by surprise ,
just as you could catch the real Alessa by surprise .
There were moments when she 'd play the little girl ,
and moments when , from the reflective look on her face ,
you felt she understood a lot more than she was letting on to .
She taught a thing or two to everyone , even to Radha Mitchell .
Radha wanted to change one of her lines ,
and Jodelle said ,
" No , if you change that line ,
" my biblical reference won 't make sense . "
It was quite an amazing thing to witness .
All it did was increase my admiration for the kid .
I 'd wanted to work with Deborah Kara Unger for a long time .
She 'd been the voice of Emu O 'Hara in Crying Freeman .
She had dubbed the young actress who was in that role ,
to give her a deeper , more sensual voice .
So I wanted to film her ,
and when I showed her the project I said ,
" Please don 't slap me ! "
She 's a very beautiful , very sensual woman , you see ,
and there I was with the project for a film ,
in which she had to play a disgusting old wreck .
So I said , " Please don 't slap me !
" You 've waited all this time ,
" and now I 'm offering you this grotty character . "
But she 's an actress , of course , so she was very interested
in playing such a radically unglamorous character .
Originally , in the game , you ended up killing Cybil yourself .
This was quite a traumatic sequence
because Cybil was the only person who 'd come and helped you .
But she got possessed and then you had to kill her .
I decided to give her a different death , a death that 's ...
much more spectacular .
She suffers a really awful torment , which is death on the ladder ,
whereby the person is tied to a ladder and burnt slowly over a fire ,
and not asphyxiated by the smoke .
It could take a very long time and is truly horrendous .
It 's a typical torture of the witch-hunting era .
When I first started going to see films , including horrors ,
films about the Inquisition were very popular .
Films about witches , their trials and executions .
It was the period just after The Devils , by Ken Russel .
That had been a big hit but very controversial ,
and a lot of films were made , especially in Italy ,
in the wake of that film .
And for me , horror and fantasy films
have always been , to some extent , about the combat between ...
Not good and evil , but the conception of good and evil .
Because films about witches
are always subversive and political .
They usually show
that witch trials were conducted in very dubious ways ,
or to keep society from changing ,
or the status of women from changing .
And I was very excited , in fact ,
at the idea of shooting this burning scene in the church ,
returning to a conception of the fantastic
which , I have to say , has practically disappeared now ,
but which I really like
because , first and foremost , that was my reference point
when I started going to see horror films .
One thing that always bothered me about these witch-burning scenes
was the crap dummy they always burnt .
It went from , " They 're burning someone , it 's horrible ! "
to , " Oh , now it 's a dummy ! "
That was something I couldn 't accept .
I couldn 't accept
that they could reduce a person 's martyrdom
to a grotesque and crude special effect .
We spent a long time making sure that Cybil 's torment
in this film was terrifying .
The moment when you expect me to cut to an old dummy ,
I show exactly what happens to someone
tied up above a bonfire .
I 'll never know how my film got a 12 rating ,
with scenes like this .
But that was to the great delight
of my distributor Samuel Hadida ,
who didn 't expect us to get such kind treatment
from the censors .
But , as I said before ,
it must have been because it 's in an imaginary world ,
it 's about a mother 's fight to save her daughter , there are no guns ...
These are all things which either annoy the censors
or pacify them .
But when you get into something
that 's overtly horrific and straightforwardly atrocious ,
you have problems . But here ...
We really didn 't expect to get off that lightly .
I 'm very proud of this scene
in terms of organising the space , how the people move and so on .
Also , as I said a little earlier ,
I had to do this whole section ,
from the burning scene onwards ...
Everything was done in a day and a half ,
including the final scene ,
the big final scene in the church , where everyone is killed by Alessa .
It was an amazing feat ,
purely in terms of organisation and logistics ,
managing to do all that in so little time .
But what I was also trying to do ,
in order to honour my contract and fit everything in ,
was shoot it really wide
- being in Cinemascope helped -
and really stand back .
It reminds me of the way
Roger Corman worked on his series of films inspired by Edgar Allen Poe ,
which he completed very quickly , sometimes in only three weeks .
What he did was film wide .
When people shoot quickly nowadays , they do it close-up .
But it 's interesting to do it quickly while shooting wide ,
as long as you have the set and the extras .
But it is another way of doing it economically .
When I first read the screenplay , the dialogues , by Roger Avary ,
I was pretty intrigued
by the fact that he 'd decided
to work the final duel between the goody and the baddy
through dialogue only .
It had to be a purely dialectical confrontation between Radha Mitchell
and Alice Krige .
I thought that was quite daring ,
because it 's not something you see very often in modern American cinema .
Duels are expressed
through physical action ,
and this was all dialectical .
And as I didn 't want to make an action movie , I was excited
at the thought of directing this scene .
Obviously , this scene ,
with Radha Mitchell saying ,
" Your faith brings death , "
was a scene which caused a few problems
with certain Americans ,
as I read on certain forums .
They probably felt that it was aimed at them ... As it was !
But besides certain fundamentalist groups in the States ,
it 's not so much Americans I 'm getting at , as all those people
who practise an intolerant religion
and who bring nothing but war , conflict and death .
So it 's not ...
Despite the film 's context ,
I think this criticism applies to all intolerant religions
and not just
to sects in the United States .
Originally , in the script ,
the door to hell that has been opened
by Radha Mitchell 's impure blood
was not going to be the portal for Alessa 's re-ascent ,
as we 'll see here ,
but was going to allow the ascent
of six judges from hell , six Red Pyramids ,
bearing various weapons ,
not just the huge sword , but also a spear ,
a mace and so on .
And the six judges from hell
would punish the ...
the members of the sect , in a sort of pastiche
of the paintings of Hieronymus Bosch ,
impaling them one after the other ,
cutting them in half lengthways and so on .
A sort of orgiastic scene ,
filmed like a mediaeval painting of hell .
Of course ,
I 'd planned to do it in several passes
because we only had one Red Pyramid , and not six .
So I 'd have had to shoot it a bit at a time ,
and sandwich it together after .
Obviously , when I heard I only had a day and a half for the ending ,
including the verbal combat we just saw ,
I realised that there was no way I could do that .
So , at the last moment , I had to rethink the final scene ,
with my storyboarder , Thierry Ségur ,
a very loyal colleague .
So we thought up a scene
which was driven by Japanese references
and inspired by Japanese animation ,
especially Urotsukidoji , Legend of the Overfiend ,
in which the forces of evil
take on a sort of octopus-like aspect .
Creatures with tentacles .
And it was with this reference , in a way , that we finished off the film .
It 's a sequence I 'm very proud of ,
not because of the result ,
but because I did it in a day and a half .
To tell the truth ,
I didn 't think I 'd finish the scene .
I could feel those insurance people watching me ,
the people from the completion bond .
They were there on the set ,
waiting to see how I could finish off the film
in less than a day .
I 'm subtracting the time it took to shoot the speeches .
So it was complicated , but we did it .
Anyway , it just goes to show
that when you have a gun pointed at your head
you can do a lot .
The idea of the bed with Alessa 's burnt body on it ,
attacking the members of the sect ,
does have a basis in the universe of Silent Hill
because the " boss " at the end of the second game
is a person in a flying bed ,
in Silent Hill 2 .
Bosses are harder to kill
than the other creatures you meet in a game .
And this boss really intrigued me ,
this character strapped into a hospital bed ,
flying above and attacking the main character .
It gave me the idea
that , rather than the six judges , it might be better if Alessa
delivers out her own vengeance .
To complete this scene in so little time , then ,
I favoured wide shots .
I remembered
not just Japanese animation , but a famous Disney film ,
Sleeping Beauty .
The idea was to try to film
the creature that has burst out of hell
like the evil thorn bush which guards Sleeping Beauty 's castle .
So I favoured wide shots ,
and favoured the movement of the thorn bush 's branches ,
or , in this case , the tentacles of barbed wire ,
within the decor .
The dynamism isn 't in the directing , but in the movement
of what would be added later : the barbed-wire tentacles .
The special effects were done , once again , by BUF .
They didn 't do all the film 's VFX .
Lots were done by Canadian companies and so on .
But they did the really big chunks of the film
where the focus was on the stylised aspect .
One moment that it was important to get right
was when Alessa confronts Sharon ,
when the dark Alessa , her evil side ,
meets her good side , Sharon ,
and the two fuse together again .
I thought it 'd be very difficult to find a young actress
who could pull off that feat , and play both at the same time .
And I think Jodelle did a great job .
The conclusion of the film , of course ,
was rather tricky to imagine .
After all the madness ,
that long journey through a dreamlike world ,
how could I finish the film ?
Going on the principle of The Twilight Zone ,
what final twist could I give to the film ?
So I went for the Judaeo-Christian explanation ,
the idea that the character is in purgatory ,
and can 't escape from that dimension .
She escaped from hell ,
but she can 't escape from the fact that maybe she 's dead
or , in any case , no longer belongs to our world ,
and remains in limbo between two worlds ,
trapped between two dimensions .
It was through thinking about certain episodes of The Twilight Zone ,
particularly one called Little Girl Lost , which inspired Poltergeist ,
an episode where a girl slipped through a crack in one dimension
and found herself stuck between our world and another ...
It was thinking about that that I imagined
the end of Silent Hill .
At the same time , I wanted a happy ending .
After all , she has found her lost daughter ,
she brings her back with her and so on .
Except that what she brings back is different from what she lost .
But I tried to respect that happy ending ,
the calm after the storm ,
the calm after the massacre of all the sect members .
In this ending there 's an idea I 've always liked in the fantastic ,
which is that ghosts are just fragments of our memories ,
that we create ghosts ourselves , with our memories ,
with our expectations and so on .
It 's an idea I came across in Amenábar 's The Others ,
a magnificent film ,
where the people you thought were the main characters
are the ghosts doing the haunting ,
although you 'd assumed by reflex that it was the other way round .
And here , in fact , Radha Mitchell 's character
will become , in a way , a ghost to her husband .
He 'll go on waiting for her but she 'll never walk in the door .
I thought it was very interesting
that you leave the film understanding that the main character
has become one of its creatures or ghosts ,
one of its most melancholic creatures .
The film came out
during a wave of horror films in the States ,
launched by Saw and other successes like Hostel .
And it 's probably because of that
that the people at TriStar
needed to get the film out ,
were nice to me and so on .
There was this idea that a European auteur or director
could bring a special sort of approach to a film ,
which was going to do well anyway .
They were absolutely certain it was going to do well .
I remember that my editor Sébastien Prangère and I
were really puzzled
by how certain the people at TriStar were ,
even as post-production begun ,
that it would do well .
And they weren 't wrong .
The film did exactly as they predicted ,
exactly as they predicted it would on the weekend of its release .
Which means that these people
had perfectly analysed the situation ,
which was that horror films were " in " again .
So the film came out during that wave and was a hit .
That wave is in decline at the moment , it 's dying down .
People have had their fill .
During that wave , one horror film a week was being released in the States .
That 's incredible .
And almost all of them did well at the box office .
When I was working on Silent Hill ,
it gave me a feeling of security to be working in that climate ,
where we were making horror films because people wanted them .
But I was also a bit obsessed
with the idea of making a horror film like no other ,
with a very distinct atmosphere and so on .
I didn 't want people to forget this film .
Love it or loathe it , but not forget it .
I 'd be annoyed if they forgot what a weird film it was .
I think that my efforts were aided , quite distinctly , by the idea
that , thanks to the material of the video game ,
this film would always remain in a class of its own ,
whatever its artistic merits might be .
A lot of people have wondered why I ended the film
with the rain falling on this bush .
In fact , that too is ...
a very Japanese shot ,
to show the character 's inner atmosphere , his melancholy .
I 'm doing what in Japanese poetry they call a haiku .
I 'm showing his inner state
simply by watching the rain falling on the vegetation .
That 's why I ended the film like that .
It was a way of defining
what the character 's life would now be :
an interminable waiting ,
thinking his wife is close by , which is sort of the case ,
but never seeing her again .
The end credits of the film are a direct homage
to the game
and its own particular aesthetic .
They were entirely designed by Kook Ewo ,
who did the flashback .
I gave the job to him . It wasn 't planned originally .
And he literally put it all together by himself ,
all on his own , sitting in a room ,
creating these amazing credits ,
which are , I think , a lovely homage to the Konami game .
I thought that was a nice way to end the film ,
reminding you of its roots ,
reminding you that the film is an adaptation
of what , in my opinion , is a genuine work of art ,
maybe a minor work of art ,
but art all the same .
I think that , in a few years ,
when the first historians of video games consider these games ,
they 'll grant Silent Hill the place it deserves ,
the place of a game that is absolutely mind-blowing ,
which has no equivalent ,
which is an original , unique work , one of a kind ,
which I was delighted to be able to adapt for the cinema .
I did it with passion .
Before being just another film ,
I think that Silent Hill
is a reflection of my passion for video games in general ,
for this oeuvre , Silent Hill , and for the people who created it .
It was my way of doffing my hat
to a parallel art ,
which , I hope ,
will be very soon be appreciated at its true value .
Well , thank you for listening to me during this film .
Keep going to see films and keep playing video games .
Bye .
Subtitles : Howard Bonsor
Subtitling : C.M.C. - Paris